let's now move to the final part and let's talk
about cloud let's talk a bit about clouds
so everyone or let's say a lot of people uses this
term cloud computing and it's a bit of a mess in
the sense that there are a lot of variations
and a lot of understandings about what this
is i'm not trying to cover all of
them here or to give an exhaustive
taxonomy of the thing especially because nowadays
it's not only about cloud computing you probably
have heard terms about IoT internet of things
edge computing fog computing and all these
things they share some similarity but they also
have different aspects and so on but if we just
focus for a moment on cloud architectures if
you put it in a very simple way the idea is that
you have a set of physical machines of servers
each of them uses virtualization to run several
guest operating systems and processes within
each guest operating system so that
companies can rely on third-party companies
that provide such virtual machines to run their
services maintain their data run their code and
so on and so forth you have of course a lot of
variations here because you can think about public
cloud infrastructures so basically
something that is what Google offers for example
or Microsoft too or private cloud infrastructures
you can have big companies that have
their own servers and they use their own
hypervisors and their own guest operating systems
to virtualize all the services they provide so
everything stays within the company but it's still
a cloud infrastructure then you have of course
different levels at which you can offer
services and we are going to look at this in
detail in the next slide you have
differences sometimes you hear talking about
big machines and small machines if you were
to let's say define a set of characteristics that
you are interested in of course
you want on-demand and self-service
provisioning of resources right so when you
need a machine you can connect and use that
machine it doesn't need to be always on always
accessible it's when you want it
(here always accessible I don't mean that you
cannot connect to it when you want what I mean is
that it doesn't need to be on and waiting for you
all the time it gets instantiated when you want)
you want broad network access right so you
want to be available via network with standard
mechanisms you don't need special hardware or
special software to connect to it you want to
create pools of resources so that you can keep
them depending on the demand you want elasticity
which is a complicated topic that we are
not covering here but the idea is that
in principle if you're running
for example certain analysis and
one core it's not enough then you should be able
to scale up the analysis by adding additional
core and increasing the parallelist degree maybe
for a while because you are observing a spike of
volume of data so you need more computational
power but then if the data goes down again in
size then maybe you can decommission some of
the cores you don't need and go back to using
less cores because it costs less and of course
you need to have a good measuring of what your
users are actually consuming what resources you are
using how much you use them because you pay only
for what you actually consume not just to keep
the machine always there and always running as
you would do probably with a traditional physical
machine that you use for a specific purpose
now these are the different type of services
you can offer so you can have the so-called
infrastructure as a service so here the idea
is that you provide the entire virtual machine
and then you connect to it remotely and
you use it it can be an ssh connection
and you just use the terminal to operate on
it or you can have a graphical user interface
you are basically connected to your computer
that is remotely maintained and run by a
hypervisor somewhere else you can have a service
that is the platform as a service here it's
not just connecting to a virtual machine but it's
connecting to a specific environment so you
can connect and use a specific operating system
you have a specific database installed there so
if you want to maintain data you already have
everything in store and a set of functionalities
that allow you to maintain the data you can make
similar examples with web servers if you want
and then you have software as a service so
in that case you are connecting to a virtual
machine but what you are using the virtual
machine for is only to execute a specific
software and this is what you are actually seeing
so you're not allowed to operate on the entire
virtual machine or go and change something in
the file system if it's about files that are
not managed by that software you just get there
to operate on a specific piece of software
now something that is a must when you
go into the cloud infrastructure that I think
it's interesting mentioning here is that of
the virtual machine migration so we said in
the very beginning of this lecture that one of the
benefits of virtualization is that if you need to
let's say do some maintenance work on your
physical server you can suspend the execution
of a virtual machine store its state and then turn
it on again start it again once you are done with
the maintenance of course you can also take the
entire virtual machine and move it to a different
piece of hardware and give it to another
hypervisor and then ask that supervisor to
execute it now the idea is simple the
problem is that of course if you are offering
a service and customers are paying only for the
amount of time or amount of resources they use
you cannot penalize them and you cannot disrupt
the service by actually turning off the machine
copying the data somewhere else and turning
on the machine again if the virtual machine
is very big that might take even minutes and
you know of course it's not really nice to
offer a service in which all of a sudden your
machine might be turned off and can be
unaccessible for a certain amount of time
especially because you might not really know
when that is going to happen and that might affect
your business so research here is conducted to
perform what is called as live migration so to
provide mechanisms that allow to transfer one
virtual machine from a certain hypervisor running
on a certain hardware to another one in a seamless
fashion the goal is that the
transition is happening but you as a user
cannot really experience or observe that this is
happening which is something that is also close
in spirit to for tolerance this is also what research on full tolerant solutions is
about many times you want to be able to tolerate
faults but without the user being affected by them
or not significantly affected by them so
now the question is how do you do this for a
virtual machine something interesting here
is the concept of checkpointing and snapshotting
so in a very simple way the idea
is that you continuously keep track of
what is changing in your virtual machine so
you have the memory and you have control of
the pages in the memory because the hypervisor is
the one that actually intercepts the request of
the guest operating system and allocates
frames on the physical memory then you
have the file system and as we said this can
actually be a file that is maintained by the
hypervisor so with checkpointing and
snapshotting the idea is that since the very
beginning of the execution of a new virtual
machine you start building an incremental
backup of all the information that is
about this virtual machine the initial
one can just be the base one because you
create a virtual machine that is let's say
the virtual machine that runs ubuntu 16 you
have an image so you can already have that as a
backup if you want to turn on a new
or create a new virtual machine with
that operating system you don't have to install
the operating system from scratch you can just
take the copy and consider that as the starting
point and then keep track of whatever is being
updated during the execution and
periodically perform updates on your backup
so that when you have to migrate something you
can start from the latest backup and only update
what was changed since the time you created
the backup to the time you are actually
performing a migration of a virtual
machine so now you need to combine
a mechanism that keeps track of
what is being modified in memory
so that you can replicate that and
apply those changes to the latest backup
but you can make everything more smooth in
the transition because you can take the last
checkpoint snapshot and move it to a different
virtual machine without really interrupting
the execution of the current virtual machine
and if you are able in a lightweight manner
to keep always incremental snapshots
with a fine-grained resolution then this
is basically the mechanism that allows
you to achieve seamless live migrations